There's a suta in a suta nipata called
sala suta the the arrow
and it's it basically speaks about uh
mortality death and loss and g grieving
>> and so just go through a few verses and
see where we go from there.
The first verse it says signless and
unpredictable is the life of mortals
here difficult and limited and conjoined with
difficult and limited and conjoined with
suffering.
>> Mhm.
>> And then verse 15 which relates to this
>> for in whatever way they conceive
>> it become it becomes otherwise of such a
sort is the nature of separation. M
>> so I like this signless and
unpredictable is the life of mortals.
It's signless
unpredictable. And I was just thinking that
And I was just thinking that
uh
that emphasis people don't emphasize
that they don't even see that that it's
unpredictable. It's like what they see
is that it's predictable. I
won't I probably won't die today.
Everything's going well. I've got things
to do tomorrow. Things I feel okay.
>> Um there's no danger here. [laughter]
It's like that that's not true. Yet that
is the sign that one lives with like
it's like a fantasy that you kind of
that sign helps you feel in a way that
things are in control. on some degree
you know what you got you got your plans
for tomorrow and so on
>> but that's not that's not a definite
thing it's not predictable
and so it's just about coming back
trying to see that that nature that that
is the there is no
um sign for
there's no nothing sure there's nothing
in your experience that's actually that
you can rely on that proves that you're
going to be here tomorrow. Like I'm I'm
healthy now. So there's a good chance I
will still be here tomorrow.
>> But well even that means doesn't mean
that you're not going to die in the next
breath. >> And so relying on that I if I rely on
>> And so relying on that I if I rely on
this if I rely on the or cultivate that
perception
of next breath I could die or I
cultivate the perception of no tomorrow
I might still be here then when things
if if I cultivate the the latter of I'm
I will probably still be here when
things do don't go according to my
expectations >> it's going to be a big massive slap in
>> it's going to be a big massive slap in
the face
>> yeah so it's like well yeah I mean
that's the that's that's that's kind the
the the outcome of your practice.
But uh if somebody
thinks they can just start contemplating
those levels now, it's not going to
work. Mhm.
>> is just too much.
>> It's well it might yeah it's going to
either be too much in terms of like
anxiety and fear that will arise on
account of it or it will be something
way too abstract that they will not be
able to sustain and it's just going to
become a mechanical kind of mantra like
repetition that oh here my next breath
and be here now and what not but none of
that carries the weight anymore. So
instead of trying to force those as I
said technically well factually kind of
um higher or more advanced ways of
contemplation you need to uh remove
everything that's preventing those types
of contemplation to be concrete for you.
Um so everything that's in the way of
you contemplating
um your experience rightly here and now
needs to be addressed first. So again,
it's like the simile of purifying the
gold like you're you're focusing on this
refined kind of precise removal of the
very fine impurities, you know, the the
ones at the deepest level while the
whole gold is still swimming in like mud
and crap and who knows what. So it's
simply not going to work. So I think
first and foremost practically a person
needs to recognize that doesn't matter
um how much you think you're living in
the present moment and what type of
effort you know you're putting in for as
long as you're not a sapana
uh your entire experience is still lived
by a fundamentally by a great deal of
projections true projections
everything you do you think you believe
you set yourself it's a projection
including discovering the dumb I wanted
to practice becomes another projection.
But obviously it's a projection that
carries a potential to turn against
itself and reveal the nature of
projections. And then you stop living
through these conceivings of things that
are fundamentally otherwise projections
or perversions whatever sort of calls
them perversions, intoxications,
whichever way you want to describe it,
that needs to be undone first for all
these correct contemplations of death
and the next breath and anapanati and
all this to actually start making sense
and and do the work it's supposed to.
Otherwise, that will become another
projection, another perversion.
So how do you do undo perversions? Well,
by recognizing the whole description of
the gradual training, what it starts
with and to start developing that. So
the you you cannot factually you cannot
doesn't matter how much effort you you
you use with tweezers to to p purify the
like like subtle impurities from gold.
If the whole liquid is still floating in
mud, you're effectually making no
difference. So the little experiences and insights
So the little experiences and insights
you might have on account of um whatever
effort you made towards understanding
dharma and go on a retreat and stuff if
what you go back to is the basis of
sensuality ill will uh not keeping the
precepts only occasionally or not fully
purified not developing it not seeing
the fault in the slight not seeing the
danger in the slightest fault and all of
that. If you have not even developed
that no amount of your work and insights
make any difference because again you go
back into the same dirt same mud which
which nullifies anything anything that
you would have cleaned supposedly
>> anyway it's like remind me of that the
danger of uh contemplating death and
nature as I'm saying
>> u while not having given up sensual
activities or calmed your mind no
precept means that that's what you go
back to That's that's almost guaranteed.
>> Well, you you don't like you wouldn't
even go back. You never leave it.
>> You never leave it.
>> So then contemplating these things were
just going to create um even more of
that tension and artificial kind of
tension and pressure. That's not because
of the contemplation, but because of the
things you're still holding dear and
refusing to let go of that are now being
threatened by the contemplation. So yes,
some degree of contemplation, some
degree of divine messengers can wake
person up from that sort of uh uh
mindless obl mindless oblivion. But uh
like fundamentally if you really want to
u transcend it and step out of it and
free yourself from it, you need to start
um tailor like like tailoring your
actions by body, speech and mind to
match that withdrawal. Not just pret
I I don't have to give these things up.
I don't have to make the effort and say
no to things first, things of sensual
nature, acting out of ill will,
distraction that I choose. And somehow
this contemplation will do that for me.
No, it's just going to create more and
more tension and basically it probably
going to result in one new type of cover
up or the other.
>> So it's like that have a wild animal and
then you you instead of training it, you
to calm down first, you show it death
and you b like these things that it
doesn't want to see that is scary
>> while it's still wild. while it can
still attack you, while it can still go
back into wilderness and make things
even worse.
>> Yeah.
>> So, it's like
>> when you're trying to catch a wild
animal, what do you do?
>> Do you go full force loud with a whip
screaming in its face and expect it to
not run away from you or attack you in
defense? >> Or do you try to like like stealth mode
>> Or do you try to like like stealth mode
come around, set up the a barrier, a
fence that the animal doesn't even know
about until it tries to escape and then
it finds the new walls around it.
Mhm. >> You already know the answer. So if you
>> You already know the answer. So if you
think you can just go into these
contemplations or perceptions while the
animal still has the free roam, well,
it's going to either attack you, as I
said, if you startle it,
>> or run away from you and then be
impossible to catch. Good luck stopping
your behavior then.
>> Yeah.
Because in in obviously in some way it's
even for a person who's
not keeping the precepts
>> not not restraint at all just getting
getting a divine messenger of oh you
know >> you got cancer now
>> you got cancer now
>> can wake them up and be like oh how am I
living my life
>> you know it's like a it's like a shock
in a
>> that doesn't necessarily make them do
worse things but it can help them like
reflect on the whole of their life why
am I doing this how
>> or do worse things it depends on the
person if they had some some initial
wisdom or some self-reflection some
transparency yes they will probably use
that >> yeah exactly
>> yeah exactly
>> uh in a more beneficial manner but more
often than not people would kind of just
try to to double down and and get the
most of what they can get until it's too
late >> yeah exactly that's probably the most
>> yeah exactly that's probably the most
common
>> reaction to
>> so yeah the question the point is not
like oh to never think about these
things because it's dangerous or
something, think about it, but recognize
that the the first thing comes first.
So, think about it. If you need an
inspiration as to why to stick to the
precepts, why to continue training in
that, why to endure the states of the
mind that try to pressure you to act out
and not act out, remind yourself of,
well, I'm dealing with obviously
fundamental existential danger that I
could actually genuinely escape if I
develop this. I can genuinely free
myself from it. But don't think that
simply through like forcing or going
through these contemplations the work of
the gradual training can be sort of you
know >> exactly that's done for you by by by by
>> exactly that's done for you by by by by
these practices. No, that's just magical
thinking basically and and and believing
in the connections when they're not
there. >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> So that's the danger of contemplation uh
of death even mindfulness of the body uh
without >> Yeah. Even the sub
>> Yeah. Even the sub
>> and honesty, self honesty.
>> Well, without the fence around your
mind, >> without the fence,
>> without the fence,
>> without the impenetrable fence of virtue
having been well established beforehand
as the would say for a long time.
>> Mhm.
Uh so just on the some other verses that
I found interesting is um verse 10, 11
and 12 it says
if the one lamenting would derive any
benefit and if the one crying would
derive any benefit then the wise one
would do that for not by weeping or by
grief does one obtain peace of mind. M
>> more arises uh more suffering arises and
the body is injured harmed through that
lamenting lean and discolored he becomes
lean and discolored he becomes
selfharming not by that of the departed
protected useless is crying. So this is
about you know the grief and the trap of
like this well performativeness
of grief grieving
>> like you and there's that whole uh
>> yeah and the point is you perform it for
yourself. It's not necessarily
performing it for others like you might
be like genuine grief is something you
do for yourself to yourself to not have
to deal with the mind that's affected by
it. Yeah, but it gets worse.
>> Exactly. It aggravates the problem.
>> Agitating yourself. And as you just
said, >> not by that are the departed protected.
>> not by that are the departed protected.
They are not helped by your grief.
>> It's [clears throat] not done for.
>> They're gone. Person's gone.
>> Yeah. So there's this uh there's that
idea of seven stages of grief that one
must go through
>> and like if you're not going through it
in a way it's like yeah there's I think
there's acceptance of what has happened.
>> Yeah. But it's like you're still
grieving. >> But this particular suta, and I think it
>> But this particular suta, and I think it
says it later on, but anyway, we might
get to that, that grief must be just
blown away.
There's no that is there's no benefit
in doing.
>> Yeah. But obviously, you can't just blow
it away. It's a state of mind. So the
mind that hasn't still overcome, the
animal that hasn't been fully tamed,
hasn't been withdrawn from dependencies
on sense objects or possessions, it will
grieve. It's more like do you take that
grief at face value and go with it and
allow it to overwhelm you or are you
able to maintain perspective in face of
it? And that's how the animal learns to
calm and not give into that because
you're not fueling it. Um, so it's Yeah.
It's not just something you could just
switch off.
>> Yeah.
But again, it's like if if one is what
we just spoke about as well, if one is
grieving, it's a kind of sign that you
>> well, there's still work to be done.
>> Yeah. And it was a surprise to you that
you lost this thing a complete like you
didn't consider that thing to the degree
that you're grieving or you haven't been
consider considering it sufficiently
enough. So
>> that's the
>> for it to sink in for it for the animal
to understand, oh yeah, it's inevitable.
Yeah. >> You can say to yourself, it's
>> You can say to yourself, it's
inevitable, but it doesn't really sink
down for the mind to hear it.
>> Why this is wrong? Why is this happening
to me?
>> Yeah. It's like a frequent recollection
of those things is necessary. It's not
just like, oh yeah, I know that. Yeah,
you know that. And now keep keep
reminding yourself of it until really
you can't forget. The animal can't
forget it. It's always there. It's
always obvious. Then it won't be able to
grieve amidst the grieving
circumstances. It won't be able to
suffer amidst not getting what it wants
or losing what what it wants.
>> So, so the degree of grief is the degree
of sort of blindness to reality
basically to the nature of things that
you >> the things that you hold dear are not
>> the things that you hold dear are not
yours.
>> Yeah. The the degree of grief reveals
the degree of projection that still
needs to be undone.
And then that obviously that
we spoke that grieving is a kind of a
you need to do it to honor the people.
>> Yeah. But those are like
>> silly worldly views basically have not
much to do with the dhamma.
>> Oh and and and there's this other point
I was thinking about that
crying almost the idea that crying and
grieving about the loss is kind of
healing for you. That's very common like
get it out, you know.
>> Yeah.
>> You cry it out and then you feel better.
>> But
>> yeah, well it goes hand in hand with a
view of that desire is something you
need to act out of cuz you make you feel
better. >> But you only you only feel you feel
>> But you only you only feel you feel
better so to speak because you're just
absolutely exhausted now. Things have
changed. You feel different.
>> Yeah. You feel exhausted but then the
pain there still the when you start
remembering when you get your energy
back you're grieving again.
>> So it doesn't heal
>> well exactly same like the desire. It's
exactly the same.
>> You stop wanting what you got cuz you
just scratched it. It went numb. Not
because you healed it. So give it some
time and it's going to start itching
again. >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Cuz you haven't really changed anything.
Well, you have changed. You made things
worse >> cuz now you need to scratch deeper and
>> cuz now you need to scratch deeper and
deeper. cry harder and harder basically.
>> Well, yeah. Or distract yourself harder
and harder
>> so that it doesn't come up the way it
comes up
>> because
>> but it's always going to catch you. It's
always going to s surprise you at some
point and you know that
>> the crying
>> grieving is a distraction
>> to this pain you feel.
>> It's a cover up cuz you don't want to
have to deal with the pressure and the
weight of the pain
>> of your attachment that now got violated
by the circumstances. Yeah.
But yeah, so not grieving
and if you actually want to
>> not giving in to grief is how you can
then >> with obviously right training not just
>> with obviously right training not just
like I won't do this but containing your
mind that wants to give into that
direction not allowing not acting out of
it like with everything else the
principles of the training do not change
is how eventually the mind will go
beyond grief and it won't be able to
grieve cuz what is there to grieve
really When every projection, every uh
When every projection, every uh
acquisition, every attachment has been
seen for what it is, has been let go of
truly um there is no more basis for any grief
um there is no more basis for any grief
or perversion that would come out of it.
>> Yeah.
And so just this few more verses uh
verse 18,
just as one would extinguish a blazing
shelter with water, thus also the firm
one possessing wisdom, the learned
skillful man would blow away quickly a
risen grief like the wind a tuft of
cotton. Yeah. So it's like the simile of
the heating up the pan. you have a cold
cold iron pan and you drop water on it
or something and it will just sit there.
It's not gonna it's not going to
evaporate. It will sit there and you
know eventually turn into a swamp. Um so
you don't just blow away the water
directly but you heat up the pan.
So that's the right practice is heating
up the pan the right things. So whatever
falls on it will evaporate instantly.
Not because you caught it in a second,
but because the pan is hot enough.
>> It seems
>> and when people don't understand that
order of training, reading the sutas
like that would sound as if like I catch
things in a millisecond as they arise.
>> Thing comes and I instantly deal with
it. It's like whack-a-ole instantly.
>> But it's no, it's the opposite. You heat
up the mind and how quickly things
disappear reveals not how quickly you
caught it but how hot the mind was, how
correctly heated up it was. So that's
same with the grief. It will be blown
away immediately
dispelled because of the the underlying
heat of the right training and the
gradual training and the development.
So you don't go around hunting things or
waiting for them to come so that you can
instantly act and and and react and show
your reflexes. No, you heat up the mind
and then you're not worried about any
water that comes on it because you know
it cannot stay there. It's going to
evaporate instantly. The hotter it is
>> and if it gets really really hot, it
can't even land on it anymore. So not
taking things as mine or see always
seeing that uh not okay obviously
precepts restraint [snorts] not adding
out a craving you you can be sure that
if my mind has diminished this aversion
and lust
>> and ignoring nature of things
>> yeah willfully ignoring aspects I don't
have to like preemptively
>> imagine things happening before I can
deal with
>> themactly It's like I am now dealing
with everything that could possibly
happen that could ever be painful. Any
loss, I'm dealing with it now.
>> Yeah.
>> Before it has occurred. So when it
occurs, it's like as you're saying, just
evaporated. And you you will you you can
and you will develop confidence in that
recognition. If the mind is trained
rightly, as I said, you don't need to go
and test and and throw water at it to
see because again, water will come one
way or the other. Um, and by that point
you would have learned where the
practice is, where the emphasis is, what
you should be heating up, what you
should kind of refrain from trying to to
react and and and and manage. And then
even if like you don't know what would
happen you know that whatever were to
happen >> it has to go through the same as I said
>> it has to go through the same as I said
>> um uh it will follow the same steps the
same procedure of falling onto the mind
>> onto the pan that's now been heated and
you're confident in its heat so you
wouldn't be afraid of things and that's
like the lion's roar you know lion does
not he's not he's lion is not afraid
[snorts] in the jungle because he has an
inventory of everybody that who's there
who comes and goes and their capacities
and what they can do to it. He's not
afraid because he doesn't he knows that
whatever it is he cannot be a danger to
me. whatever whoever. So that's the
confidence and like you know walks
around like a king of the jungle and
stuff like that
>> right
>> because so when you have confidence in
the right training the gradual training
that you develop rightly the properly
sufficiently uh suitably heated pan you
don't need to keep an inventory of all
the possibilities and everything that
could come and how about this and how
about that because you know that
whatever it comes has to come through
this entrance that's been sufficiently
correctly developed hot and and it will
be scorched away basically without your
any effort. Your effort has been made
beforehand of heating it up. Now you
don't need to be quickly wiping the the
the drops of water that fell on it.
>> You just need to make sure that you
don't uh through your own choices and
negligence cool down the pan.
>> Yeah. That that tapas that the actual
>> the actual Yes. The actual burning of of
the defilements. Yeah. You're creating
this just burns away every everything.
>> Yeah. And like the the foremost of those
tapas practices was ki patient endurance
or enduring things on the right level as
we say.
>> Yeah.
>> I think uh one of the last verses 19 and
20. One who seeks their own happiness
would pluck out their own dart. The
wailing and moaning the sad and sadness
inside. with dart plucked out unattached
having found peace of mind overcoming
also one is sorrowless and quenched. Self-explanatory. Yeah.